SHINSHINMARU 88
（第八十八新進丸）
[Hansuke] Tanba-san agreed to the offer to move out.
丹羽先生答應要搬遷了
Oh, Tanba-san.
啊，丹羽先生
-[Tanba-san] Hi. -[chuckles]
嗨
Write something on it.
寫點什麼吧
[news reporter 1] It's that time of year again.
又到了每年的這個季節
The day marking 13 years since The What.
納尼發生至今已過了13年
At this temporary housing,
在臨時住宅這裡
steps are being taken to finally move everyone out.
終於開始採取措施，推動住戶搬遷
Talks with residents are making progress.
相關人員正陸續對住戶們進行勸說
SPECIAL REPORT 13 YEARS LATER, EVICTION TALKS BEGIN
（特輯，13年過去後 開始勸說搬遷）
Some of the residents are set to move out today.
今天似乎也有住戶要離開這裡
-See you later. Bye. -[Yoshie] Call us if you need anything.
-再見… -有什麼事就打給我
Tora, get down, you dumb cat.
阿虎，下來啦，笨貓
-See you later. -[Hansuke] Bye.
-我先走了 -好
-Take care of yourself, Tanba-san. -[Yoshie] See you around.
-丹羽先生，要保重身體啊 -再見囉
-Eat properly, Tanba-san. -Goodbye, Tanba-san.
-要好好吃飯哦，丹羽先生 -再見，丹羽先生
-See you. -Bye.
-再見 -拜拜
Thirteen years, huh?
13年了嗎？
I've been here for exactly a year.
我來這裡滿1年了
PLAYING SHOGI WITHOUT PAWNS IS PLAYING A LOSING GAME OF SHOGI
（若將棋棋盤沒有步兵 棋局則無勝算，丹羽）
[news reporter 2] Even now, disaster victims are forced to live
許多災民至今仍被迫 在臨時住宅過著不便的生活
AT ITS PEAK, 30 FAMILIES LIVED HERE
（最多時有30戶居住）
Thirteen years after The What,
自納尼發生屆滿13年之際
what are the residents thinking now?
他們心裡在想些什麼呢？
[Hansuke] Tatsuya works with an intermediary
辰也跟著仲介，一戶一戶上門勸說
Neither the national nor local governments can force you out.
不管是中央政府還是地方政府 都無法強制趕走你們
But Tanba-san left.
可是丹羽先生都搬出去了
What's Masuo saying?
大哥說了什麼？
[Igawa] Everyone receives 50,000 yen for vacating.
搬遷費一律是五萬圓
That's nothin'! It's only a month's rent at the Recovery Public Housing.
那麼少！只夠付復興住宅 一個月的房租
And two masks.
還有兩枚口罩
[Mitsuyo] You can keep 'em!
誰要啊！
We'll leave, if we can live across from Hatsu in the new place.
要我搬可以啊
It's not that nice?
聽說沒那麼舒適？
I had a look inside, but the shower pressure was weak.
我有去看過裡面
-And the tatami mats were gaudy. -And they want 50,000 yen for rent?
-榻榻米還破破爛爛的 -這樣還要收五萬，那麼貴
Good morning.
各位早安
Hello.
你好
You making progress?
有進展嗎？
Next, we've got a meeting with the construction company.
我現在要去和建商開會
There are a ton of issues.
有一堆問題在等著我去解決
We'll go to Building Four.
我們要去拜訪四號棟
You sure better.
快走吧
And I thought he was a nice guy.
我還以為他是個好人
Looks like it might rain today.
今天看起來會下雨
Too bad he's behind all of it.
沒想到他就是幕後黑手
Yeah.
就是說啊
A TOWN WITHOUT SEASONS
（沒有季節的城市）
[Hansuke] The first one who displayed opposition
最初面露難色的
was someone unexpected.
是大家意想不到的那個人
I can't do this.
我會很困擾
I already barely make enough to support a family of eight.
我賺的錢付完八個家人的生活費 就差不多見底了
How could I pay rent?
哪有錢付房租啊？
Children are calculated at two-for-one, so yours is a family of five.
小孩兩個人算一個 所以您的家庭是五個人
Huh?
什麼？
If you economize, it's not an unreasonable amount to pay.
只要節省一點 這個金額不會付不出來呀
We'll assist you.
我們一起努力吧
How dare you drop in all of a sudden and tell us to leave this month.
突然上門來 還叫我們在這個月搬出去
Are you devils? You may as well tell us to die.
你們是魔鬼啊？
[Igawa] The government provided this interim housing as temporary relief
國家提供臨時的住處是暫時性的支援
until families got on their feet.
只給各位住到能自力更生為止
Can't you see? We're not on our feet yet.
你看不出來嗎？我們還不能自力更生
-Then quit having babies. -Cut that out, Hamaguchi.
-誰叫你生那麼多個 -別說了，濱口
Sorry.
抱歉
In this time of shrinking population, I admire you.
在少子化的時代 我覺得您這樣很了不起
But from our view--
不過我們…
-You understand how it is, right? -Huh?
-你應該懂吧？ -什麼？
You support your mom and two siblings.
你有媽媽和兩個弟妹要養
[Ryotaro] It's not easy, is it?
一點都不輕鬆吧？
Actually… they all left.
我們家的人已經搬出來了
You're kidding?
你搞什麼？
Got out early, huh?
偷偷先搬走啊？
You and your Young Men's Club,
說什麼是青年部的
you said you'll make us a cafe and stuff.
還說要開咖啡廳
But now you're on their side, pressuring us to get out.
結果還不是和他們站在一起壓榨我們
You traitor!
你這個叛徒！
Aren't you getting child-support payments, ma'am?
你難道沒有拿撫養費嗎？太太
Mikki.
阿三先生
[Mikki] I had you people investigated.
我查過你們每個人的資料了
Tsutomu, Shiro. Go play outside.
小勉、志郎，去外面玩
[Mikki] They're not your kids, right?
他們不是你的小孩對吧？
Hey, cut that out.
等等，不要這樣
Their real fathers are all residents here, right?
他們真正的父親都是這裡的居民吧？
-You're really something, ma'am. -[Tatsuya] Cut it out!
-太太，你真不簡單啊 -夠了！
If each of their fathers paid 10,000 yen a month,
這些孩子的五位父親 每個月各自出一萬圓
you could pay that rent.
不就付得起房租了嗎？
Right, Sprouts?
對不對？蘿蔔芽
Are you deaf? Go play outside! Now!
沒聽到是不是？ 叫你們去外面玩，快點！
They don't have to go.
不用去！
I'm sure you kids know
你們應該都知道
who your real father is and who's a liar.
誰才是你們真正的爸爸，誰又在說謊
Isn't that right?
對不對？
Ryoko, tell them your father's name.
涼子，說說看老爸叫什麼名字
Ryotaro Sawagami.
澤上良太郎
What? Are you kidding? She's clearly half Japanese.
拜託，她怎麼看都是混血兒啊
That Indian laborer's her dad.
她爸是那個印度勞工吧
Nobody asked you!
沒人問你啦！
-[Tatsuya] Whoa, stop! -Nobody asked you!
-住手啦！ -誰叫你說話了！
-Get out! -[Hamaguchi] Stop it!
-給我滾！ -不要這樣！
[Ryotaro] Get out right now!
現在馬上滾出去！
[Mikki] I only addressed the elephant in the room.
我只是實話實說啊
[Hansuke] That night, Misao Sawagami, aka Sprouts,
那天晚上，蘿蔔芽 也就是澤上美沙緒
left the town with just her baby.
只帶著嬰兒離開這座城市
[in Hindi] Farewell.
再會
[Hansuke in Japanese] The Immigration Bureau arrested Ryoko's father
入國管理局以非法工作的罪名
for the crime of illegal employment.
將涼子的父親帶走了
Farewell.
再見
[in Japanese] It's not your fault, Hansuke.
阿半，這不是你的錯
No, it definitely is.
不，就是我的錯
[Tatsuya] Sooner or later, it would've come out.
這是遲早的事啦
Just nobody ever told anyone.
大家都知道，只是不說
You're wrong. Staying silent is a great thing.
不對，能夠不說出來很不簡單啊
Ignoring it is kindness.
有時候漠視反而是一種溫柔啊
How can you stay silent? People like Roku-chan and Kuma
我沒辦法忍住不說 因為他們不正常啊，像是阿六
and Sprouts aren't normal. We want to talk about them.
還有阿熊先生、蘿蔔芽
And you'll get paid if you report it.
而且去回報還有錢可拿嘛
I was being arrogant.
是我太傲慢了
Since I'm a good and proper person,
“因為我是個正常 會做出正確之舉的好人
I can do whatever I want to people who aren't.
所以要對跟我不一樣的人 做什麼都可以”
I felt that way inside.
以前我心裡是這麼想的
So I want to apologize to everyone.
所以我想向大家道歉
Everyone? Who?
你說的“大家”是誰？
Everyone's gotta leave because of you!
大家都因為你，要被趕走了啊！
Tanba-san,
丹羽先生
and Hatsu and Masuo
阿初和益夫先生
and Roku-chan
阿六
and Katsuko.
還有克子
Huh? Is that right, Katsuko?
什麼？小克，真的嗎？
That CEO's wife, her mom, said she'll take her in for a while.
社長夫人，也就是她的媽媽
I'm sorry.
對不起
What are you apologizing for?
幹嘛道歉啦？
It is a shock though.
雖然我是很震驚啦
It's only a matter of time before the complainers leave.
那些在抱怨的人遲早也會搬走
The ones who don't pay taxes, the ones on welfare illegally.
沒繳稅的人
Look and you'll find dirt on all of them.
仔細查會發現大家身上都有汙點
That's why nobody talked. Not because they're kind!
所以大家才忍著不說 才不是因為心地善良
Why are they being kicked out? What'll be built here?
把他們趕走要做什麼？ 這裡到底要蓋什麼？
[Shima] Memorial Stadium.
紀念體育館
It'll open this summer.
將於今年夏天開業
We'll hold a festival to celebrate the reconstruction.
會舉辦復興紀念的音樂節
NANI ROCK FES. 2024
（納尼搖滾音樂節2024）
[Okabe] That's really scuzzy.
感覺很可疑
The headliner will be Maximum the Hormone.
壓軸的是極限荷爾蒙樂團
Wait. Hold on here.
等等，先等一下
This place is too small for a stadium.
這塊地蓋體育館太小了吧
[Shima] That's why it's being built on the waterfront where access is better.
所以會蓋在交通更方便的海岸地帶
The performers' dressing rooms, a parking lot,
這裡會是藝人的休息室
and porta potties will be located here.
停車場和流動廁所的場所
You don't need this space for that. It could go anywhere!
那種東西蓋在其他地方也可以啊！
Porta potties and dressing rooms for a festival?
這裡是音樂節的廁所？休息室？
You're kicking everyone out for that?
為了那些就要把大家趕走嗎？
Tanaka, I'll admit that this is a nice place,
田中，我也覺得這裡是個好地方沒錯
but it's not a utopia.
但不是烏托邦
It's temporary housing.
這裡是臨時的住處
Normal people move out of here.
正常人都會離開這種地方
Sorry.
抱歉
I need you to sign this agreement by tomorrow.
誓約書要簽名，最晚明天要交
[Hansuke] I've got a lot of stuff now.
家裡多了好多東西
[Tora] They're all presents though.
雖然全部都是別人給的
What should I do?
怎麼辦？
Where the heck am I supposed to go?
是要叫我搬去哪裡啊？
[Tora] It'll work out somehow.
船到橋頭自然直啦
Are you coming with me?
你也要跟我走嗎？
[Tora] What? You'd leave me behind?
什麼？難道你要丟下我嗎？
Oh, there's a QR code.
啊，QR碼
AGREEMENT TO VACATE TEMPORARY HOUSING
（臨時住宅搬離誓約書）
NO SEASON SENT YOU 50,000 YEN
（無季節匯入五萬圓）
[Hansuke] The payment for vacating was paid in digital cash.
搬遷費以電子貨幣支付給我了
The elderly who didn't have cell phones received 50,000 yen in gift certificates.
對於沒有智慧型手機的年長者 會配發五萬圓的商品券
And here are two masks.
兩枚口罩
Thank you for residing here for 13 years.
13年來辛苦了
Thank you.
謝謝
For you, Roku-chan, you get 50,000 yen on a train pass card.
阿六的是這個
Ride all you want.
可以坐電車坐到膩
How dare she make fun of me.
瞧不起我啊？
I'm not into trains!
我才不要搭電車
Power shovels are the best!
挖土機最棒了！
[Kuniko] Roku-chan, carry this for me.
阿六，這個幫我端過去
There. Okay, let's go.
好，我們走吧
Over there. There.
端去那邊…
[noisy chatter]
大哥…
[Hansuke] On the last day,
在最後一天
No Season held a farewell party.
舉行了無季節主辦的惜別會
THANK YOU FOR RESIDING HERE FOR 13 YEARS! FOR OUR SUSTAINABLE FUTURE!!
（邁向永續的未來！ 各位13年來辛苦了）
Would you like a drink?
可以喝一杯嗎？
Hey! Cut that out, darn it! Quit throwing things!
你們不要鬧了！
That No Season…
我說無季節啊…
Thank you.
謝謝
[noisy chatter continues]
-好 -你們要吃嗎？
Hey! Get outta here!
喂！臭貓！
-Shoo! Shoo! -Yeah, yeah.
-走開… -好啦…
Any place is fine. Any place.
隨便，寫哪都可以
Hasegawa. Bartender. You guys write something too.
長谷川先生、老闆 你們也來寫點什麼吧
-[Hasegawa] Are you sure it's okay? -Of course.
-可以嗎？ -當然了
Thank you.
謝謝
Don't make any mistakes.
不要寫錯字
-Let's go. -Okay.
-走吧 -好
[Hansuke] Tora!
阿虎！
We should have invited Tanba-san.
要是也找丹羽先生來就好了
Wanna call him?
打電話給他看看吧
Didn't you know, Hansuke?
阿半，你不知道嗎？
Tanba-san went to live in a nursing home.
丹羽先生搬去安養院了
What? Not the public housing?
什麼？他不是搬去復興住宅？
[Tatsuya] They said he's got dementia.
他們說他有失智症
And that he can't live alone anymore.
應該沒辦法再自己一個人住了
Are you kidding? He was living alone.
開什麼玩笑？ 他在這裡就是一個人住啊
He was just fine.
他過得很好啊
Tatsuya, is Shima-san inside?
辰也，島先生在裡面嗎？
[Tatsuya] Whoa! Yes, he is, but he's in a video meeting.
在是在啦，可是他正在開視訊會議
Huh?
什麼？
He sends his greetings.
他要我代他向你們問好
-Not like I care. -I gotta go to the restroom.
-我是不在意啦 -我去一下廁所
But what's more important than giving us a proper farewell?
有什麼事比向我們問好還重要？
Now, now, Masuo. Let's keep on drinkin'.
好了啦，大哥，我們繼續喝
[Masuo] Just like you people want, we'll be leavin' tomorrow.
我們明天就會搬出去 這樣你滿意了吧
Scum of the earth!
老子不爽！
THE VERTICAL THREAD IS KATSUKO THE HORIZONTAL THREAD IS OKABE
（縱線是克子，橫線是岡部）
Katsuko, can you come here?
姐姐，過來一下
There's a 'coon dog.
那邊有狸喵
[Katsuko] "Coon dog"?
“狸喵”？
[Kuma] Get outta here, you caterpillar.
怪手給我閃遠一點啦
Nobody wants you here.
真是礙事
[Hansuke] Kuma, calm down and enjoy your drink.
阿熊先生，冷靜下來慢慢喝吧
[Kuma] I'm leavin' after I finish this one anyway.
我把這杯喝完就要走了
What the heck are you filming, you media scum?
拍什麼拍啊？爛媒體！
Quit filmin'!
不准拍！
I'm an ex-con, ya know, dammit!
我有前科啦，混蛋！
[Ryotaro] How pathetic.
笑死人了
You killed someone and buried 'em, huh?
你說你砍過人，還埋屍過？
What a stupid lie that is.
說這種無聊的謊話
I bet you went to prison for stealin' panties.
你的前科不是偷內衣嗎？
How pathetic.
有夠好笑
-Hansuke. You seen Katsuko? -[Hansuke] No.
阿半
She was by the boat banner.
她剛才在大漁旗那裡
[Okabe] Really?
真的嗎？
Then I've got a really funny lie for you, you husband of a whore.
那我就跟你說一個好笑的謊
-Don't say that. -[Hansuke] Stop it. What's wrong?
-別說了 -等一下，你怎麼了？
[Kuma] Got a problem with that?
怎麼樣啊？
Where is it?
在哪裡？
Sorry.
對不起
[Okabe] Katsuko?
小克？
Don't shout!
不准叫！
I dare you to say that again!
你再說一次試試看！
I'll say it a hundred times!
要我說幾次都可以啊！
Your girl Mariko, I planted the seed for her. She's my kid!
你家的真理子
That's a load of crap! You're full of crap!
誰會相信你！
You guys tell him too.
你們也告訴他啊
You'll never be seein' each other again anyway.
反正以後也不會再見面啦
You all porked her! You're Shiro's dad!
你們也上過她啊！
You're Rika's dad!
還有梨花她爸！
You've got it reversed!
你說反了！
Ryotaro, I'm so ashamed!
阿良先生，我對不起你！
Holy shit.
可惡啊
You're all bastards!
你們這些混帳！
[Masuo] An Olympic flame, huh?
要傳聖火嗎？
[Ryotaro] You bastards!
混帳！
Hurry up and do something!
老公，快點想想辦法啊！
[Hatsutaro] Shut up, you hussy!
吵死了，你這個臭女人！
You've been sleepin' with Masuo, ain't ya?
你跟大哥睡過了吧？
What?
什麼？
You have?
是真的嗎？
How can you say that, Mitsuyo? What proof do you have?
小光，怎麼連你也這樣？ 你有什麼證據啊？
I've got proof!
證據我有！
I've watched a ton of porn about cheatin' wives. I studied them.
我在影音包廂看遍 妻子被別人睡走的色情片，做過研究
That's my proof!
那就是證據！
-What? -See?
-什麼鬼話？ -怎樣啦？
Admit it.
你就承認吧
Ask this guy. He knows!
問這傢伙就知道啦！
It was you, you shorts-wearing scumbag!
就是你，穿短褲的混蛋！
You were nosing around in all our business.
是你在到處探聽我們的祕密吧？
[Hatsutaro] Is that right?
是這樣嗎？
[Kuma] I thought somethin' was fishy.
我早就覺得可疑了
There's nobody nowadays who wants to live in temporary housing.
哪有人現在才想住進臨時住宅
You're a spy for No Season!
你是無季節的間諜吧？
-Huh? -A spy?
-什麼？ -間諜？
That's right.
沒錯
That's enough, Hansuke.
夠了，阿半
I sold your personal info
我出賣大家的個資
and was paid money by that man!
跟那個人拿錢！
I'm sorry!
我對不起大家！
Auntie! Auntie! It's Katsuko! She's…
伯母！
What's wrong, Okabe?
岡部，你說什麼？怎麼了？
The kids have barricaded themselves inside the school building.
孩子們佔領校舍了
-Huh? -What?
-什麼？
-[Okabe] This way! -[Hasegawa] Ryotaro!
-這邊！ -阿良先生！
Katsuko!
小克！
What's all this?
這是怎麼回事？
Watch out! What the heck are you doing?
危險！你們在幹什麼？
STAY BACK
（不准過來！）
Hey!
喂！
You okay?
你還好嗎？
[children] ♪ Lingering like a juicy tomato ♪
（回味無窮，就像多汁番茄）
♪ The fickle salad missed the train ♪
（來不及上隨興沙拉）
It's the Veggie Girls.
是蔬菜女孩的歌
♪ While I cry in the triangle corner ♪
（只能在水槽三角形的角落哭泣）
Sprouts!
蘿蔔芽！
Katsuko!
小克！
Tsutomu!
小勉！
-Stay back! -[screaming]
不准過來！
[Tsutomu] Stay back!
你們不要過來！
We don't want to leave here!
我們不想離開這裡！
We wanna stay here forever!
我們想要一直待在這裡！
You can't.
不行啦
They'll start tearing it down tomorrow.
明天就會開始拆遷了
You can't live here!
這裡已經不能住了！
No! I like it here!
不要，我們要住在這裡！
Why do you like it here?
為什麼一定要住在這？
It's where Mom and Dad met.
因為這裡是老爸和老媽認識的地方
[Mariko] We were all born here. This is all we know.
大家都在這裡出生，只知道這個地方
So we don't wanna go anywhere else.
所以不想去其他地方
Even if it is better than here, I don't want us to split up!
就算其他地方比這裡好 我們也不想要分開住！
We talked it over yesterday and made up our minds to stay here!
我們昨天討論好的 一定要留在這裡！
Mariko…
真理子
I understand.
我明白
I understand how you feel.
我明白你們的心情
This place is all I've got too.
叔叔也只有這個地方可以住
My whole family died.
叔叔的家人都死了
All I had was my cat when I came here.
和貓咪一起來這裡
And you know what?
叔叔更慘喔
My family abandoned me.
被家人拋棄了
So we understand.
所以我們都明白
It's called temporary housing, but to all of you, it's not temporary.
雖然叫做臨時住宅
But this doesn't involve Katsuko, right?
不過這跟克子姊姊沒關係，對不對？
Yes, it does.
有關係啊
When we're hungry, we'll eat her.
如果肚子餓了 我們會把這個姊姊殺來吃
-What? -Eat her?
-什麼？ -會吃她嗎？
We won't eat her.
不會吃
We're not going to eat her.
不是要吃她啦
She meant to say that we'll have her cook for us.
她是說要請姊姊煮飯給我們吃
We're not going to split up.
我們不會分開住啊
You're lying! Now that Mom's gone, if we're kicked outta here,
騙人，老媽都離開了 如果我們還被趕出這裡
there's no way we'll be able to live together again.
不就沒有理由一起住了嗎？
Yeah, if you weren't my children.
當然會一起住 除非你們不當老爸的小孩
Of course,
老爸我當然…
I know I'm your father.
都把你們當成自己的小孩
But if you don't believe that,
但如果你們不想當老爸的小孩
then have the man who you think is your real father take care of you.
那就去找你覺得是親生爸爸的人疼你
Hey!
喂！
What about you, Dad?
那老爸呢？
I'll have to live alone.
只能自己一個人過了
It's unfair to take care of just one of you.
如果只疼你們其中一個人就不公平啦
Either all together, or split up.
要就大家住在一起
It's either one.
只有這兩條路
No!
不要！
No, no!
不要…
All together is best!
我要大家住在一起！
We're all your kids, Dad!
大家都是老爸的小孩啊！
-[Tsutomu] Dad! -[Mariko] Dad!
-老爸！
-Thank you, you guys. -Dad!
-謝謝你們
Ryotaro Sawagami.
澤上良太郎
[Ryotaro] That's right. Ryotaro Sawagami.
對，澤上良太郎
What'll I do? I don't wanna leave here either.
怎麼辦？我也不想搬離這裡
You've got no choice.
我有什麼辦法嘛
I doubt there's anywhere better than this.
我覺得不會有比這裡更好的地方
-You've only been here a year. -But I've gotta go, right?
-明明只住一年而已 -不搬走不行，對不對？
Yep.
對
Do I go out quietly or do I go out fighting?
我要安靜地搬走 還是要吵吵鬧鬧地離開？
Fighting?
吵吵鬧鬧？
-[screams] -Whoa! You scared me!
嚇我一跳！
I've had enough of this!
開什麼玩笑！
-[Tatsuya] Hey! Stop! Stop! -[Hansuke] Outta my way!
-等一下！等等！ -讓開！
Back off! Back off, you scum!
走開！你們給我走開！
Back off!
全都走開！
This is mine!
這是我的！
This belongs to me! It's mine!
是我的東西，給我！
-Hey! -Let go!
-喂！ -放開！
[worker] What do you think you're doing?
你在幹嘛？
What the heck have you done?
你看你做的好事！
[Tatsuya] Quit filming! You're trespassing!
不准拍！你這是非法入侵！
[Mitsuyo] Stop it! Stop it!
住手…
[Kuniko] Roku-chan's missing!
阿六不見了！
[Tatsuya] One at a time, please!
拜託一個一個來！
My husband got drunk and set fire to Shima-san's place!
我家那位喝醉 去島先生的家放火了！
Hansuke!
阿半！
-Hansuke! -[Mitsuyo] This way!
-阿半！ -這邊…
-[Hansuke] Shima-san! -[Masuo] At last, you came out.
-島先生… -終於出來了
At last, you came out.
終於逃出來了
It'll be fine. They're tearing it down anyway.
沒關係，反正都要拆了
-This'll make it easier. -My sweet wife!
-燒一燒比較好拆啦 -我的妻子！
-Have a drink. -My sweet wife's inside!
-喝酒吧 -我的妻子還在裡面！
What? Why didn't you say so sooner?
什麼？你幹嘛不早說？
No, Shima-san!
不要啊，島先生！
Oh no! What have I done?
完了，我搞砸了！
-Hatsu, what have I done? -Fire extinguisher!
-阿初，我搞砸了！ -滅火器！
Get a fire extinguisher!
快拿滅火器過來！
You need the fire department.
要叫消防車才滅得了火
The wind's pretty strong, so it'll burn quickly.
畢竟風很大，所以燒得很快
Huh?
什麼？
Hurry up and call the fire department.
快點打電話給消防車啊
Roku-chan?
阿六？
-[Hansuke] Shima-san! -[screaming]
島先生！
Hansuke!
半助！
-[Shima's wife] I've got no choice now. -[Yoshie] Huh?
看來我別無選擇了
Oh my God!
不要啊！
Watch out! Watch out!
危險，小心啊！
Okay! Bring it on!
要打架是不是？來啊！
I don't know how.
我不知道
I don't know how to stop it!
我不知道怎麼停下來！
-Roku-chan!
-阿六！
-[uproarious shouting]
阿六！
Mom!
媽媽！
-Mom… -[explosion]
媽…
I'm sick of this!
我玩膩了！
Trains are better after all.
還是電車比較好
Hey!
喂！
-Mom! Mom! -Roku-chan!
-媽媽… -阿六！
Mom! Mom!
媽媽…
-Are you hurt anywhere? -No.
-有沒有哪裡受傷？ -沒有
[resident 1] Hansuke! You okay?
半助，你還好嗎？
[Tatsuya] Hansuke!
阿半…
[resident 1] Is he dead?
他死了嗎？
[Tatsuya] He's alive! Hansuke!
還活著，阿半…
[resident 2] It's all burning down. Oh, dear!
全都燒光了，天啊！
Awesome!
太棒啦！
We did it!
辦到啦！
[Hansuke] And that's how we went out fighting.
我們就這樣
SQUATTERS IN TEMPORARY HOUSING BURN AND RIOT
（臨時住宅的居民縱火暴動 令和時代的貧民窟）
The riot that day got replayed again and again on tabloid TV shows.
那天的騷動在電視上不斷重播
It went viral for a week on social media.
並在網路上瘋傳將近一星期
[Tatsuya] You're trespassing!
你這是非法入侵！
Long after that,
過了很久以後
the former residents never spoke about how they lived in that town.
居民們對曾經住在那座城市 一事絕口不提
Even if they crossed paths,
即使在外碰巧遇到
they would absolutely never talk to each other.
也絕對不會向對方搭話
It was an unwritten rule.
那是大家不成文的默契
Don't interfere with
對於抹除過去的經歷
former friends hiding their past and blending into society.
融入社會打拚的夥伴，不可前去打擾
See how it looks in the mirror.
可以在鏡子前面看看
That's lovely. Are you looking for a top?
很適合您，您想找上衣嗎？
The event commemorating reconstruction was ultimately never held.
復興紀念的活動最後並沒有舉辦
The town without seasons no longer exists.
沒有季節的城市
There is one thing that they did learn.
不過他們很清楚一件事
There is no worse way to live.
沒有比那裡更糟糕的生活
But there is also no more human way to live.
但是那種生活方式也最像個人
I see.
原來如此
Personally, I like it.
我自己是挺喜歡的
But it can't be published like this.
但是這樣的作品我們沒辦法刊登
[editor] Mr. Tanaka?
田中先生？
Yeah, you're right.
我想也是
The characters are captivating.
角色是很有魅力啦
Like the homeless father and son and train crazy Roku-chan.
像是無家可歸的流浪漢父子 或是電車迷阿六
A TOWN WITHOUT SEASONS
（《沒有季節的城市》）
People like that don't exist.
現實生活中絕對不會有這種人
But ethically,
但是在道德上
"ganmodoki" and "sprouts" won't do.
油豆腐、蘿蔔芽
Disrespecting women is a problem. I liked those though.
這些歧視女性的部分會有問題
Next time, please write something heartwarming where nobody gets hurt.
下次請寫一些溫暖風格 沒有人會受傷的故事
Thank you for coming all this way.
不好意思讓你白跑一趟
Thank you.
謝謝你
PLAYING SHOGI WITHOUT PAWNS IS PLAYING A LOSING GAME OF SHOGI
（若將棋棋盤沒有步兵 棋局則無勝算）
THE END
（劇終）
Translated by Brian Athey
字幕翻譯：劉翠恬